{"tossups": [{"question": "The heresy of Adoptionism was created by this city\u2019s archbishop Elipandus. In one legend, this city\u2019s Alcazar fortress refused to surrender, even after Jose Moscardo\u2019s son was taken for ransom. This European city produced swords used by both Hannibal\u2019s Carthaginians and the Roman legions; those swords were made of a steel alloy that was unmatched until the discovery of Damascus steel in the Middle Ages. For ten points, name this city in central Spain that was once called the \u201cImperial City\u201d as the seat of Charles V\u2019s court.", "answer": "<b> Toledo</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This city\u2019s government lost the Supreme Court case<em> Ricci v. DeStefano</em> against a group of firefighters who were not promoted despite passing qualification tests. In this city, James Hillhouse established the first public tree planting project in America, leading it to be nicknamed \u201cThe Elm City.\u201d This city was the birthplace of a group known as \u201cOrder 322\u201d or \u201cSkull and Bones,\u201d whose collegiate members included John Kerry and George W. Bush. For ten points, name this Connecticut city that is home to Yale University.", "answer": "<b> New Haven</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This ship was sent to patrol the Burdwood Bank on what would be its final mission. This ship was formally commissioned as the USS<em> Phoenix</em>, but was eventually sold off for the People\u2019s Loyalty Day celebration. After this ship was sunk,<em> The Sun</em> published an infamous headline that read \u201cOur lads sink gunboat and hole cruiser.\u201d The \u201cGotcha!\u201d headline trumpeted the sinking of this ship, the first ever to be sunk by a nuclear submarine. A general who fought for Argentine independence names, for ten points, what ship that was sunk during the Falklands War?", "answer": "ARA General<b> Belgrano</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "An 1887 experiment involving a block of sandstone floating in mercury failed to find the fringe shift expected by a \u201cwind\u201d generated by this substance. This substance is supposed to be dragged by the Earth moving through it, a process not detected by the Michelson-Morley experiment. The theory of relativity was able to explain the non-existence of, for ten points, what hypothetical substance through which light moves, according to a theory that was finally debunked in the early 20th century?", "answer": "luminiferous a<b>ether</b>", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {}, {"question": "An opera titled for one of these people ends with a chorus singing \u201cGlory, Glory to you.\u201d One of these people falls in love with Marfa in a Rimski-Korsakov opera titled for one of these people\u2019s<em> Bride</em>. The hero Susanin leads Poles into a blizzard in a Mikhail Glinka opera titled<em> A Life for</em> one of these people. The song \u201cflow, flow bitter tears\u201d ends a Modest Mussorgsky opera in which one of these leaders gives the throne to his son Fyodor. Boris Godunov held, for ten points, what position that was abolished with the fall of the Romanovs?", "answer": "<b> tsar</b> of Russia (or<b> czar</b> of Russia; prompt on partial answers, including \u201cemperor of Russia\u201d)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A settlement known as Keshet was created on the grounds where this region\u2019s primary city of Quneitra had been burned to the ground. The southern portion of Mount Hermon extends into this region, where the Purple Line was created after a ceasefire during the 1973 Yom Kippur War. In the aftermath of a 1967 war, over 100,000 refugees fled this region. For ten points, name this plateau region of the Levant that Israel captured from Syria during the Six Day War.", "answer": "<b> Golan</b> Heights", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man was lampooned as an \u201canti-poverty czar\u201d by Jack Anderson while Director of the Office of Economic Opportunity under Nixon. This man replaced James Schlesinger after the Halloween Massacre, becoming the youngest Secretary of Defense in U.S. history. This man\u2019s visit with Saddam Hussein during the Reagan administration came under scrutiny during his later second term as Defense Secretary, when he oversaw the Abu Ghraib prison complex. For ten points, name this Secretary of Defense under George W. Bush who oversaw the wars in Afghanistan and Iraq.", "answer": "Donald<b> Rumsfeld</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This group conspired with Amalric of Tyre to overthrow Henry II of Cyprus. This group was allowed to pay no taxes and travel freely across borders by Pope Innocent II\u2019s papal bull<em> Omne Datum Optimum</em>, which may have been prompted by support from this group\u2019s patron, Bernard of Clairvaux. This group relieved Baldwin IV\u2019s forces at Montgisard. Members of this group were arrested for heresy by Philip IV, after which many joined the Knights Hospitaller. For ten points, name this chivalric order active in the crusades.", "answer": "<b> Knights Templar</b> (or<b> The Poor Fellow-Soldiers of Christ and of the Temple of Solomon</b>; accept<b> Order of Soloman\u2019s Temple</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "One of these events that affected the Selk\u2019nam in the Tierra del Fuego was led by Romanian-Argentine engineer Julius Popper, who designed the city of Havana. Dmitry Milyutin carried out one of these events, forcing many Circassians to be quarantined in lazarettos in the Ottoman Empire. Lothar von Trotha committed one of these actions in Namibia after the Herero and the Nama rebelled against German rule, and another of these events occurred in modern Sudan in the Darfur region. For ten points, give this term for an atrocity against an entire racial group, such as the Holocaust.", "answer": "<b> genocide</b>s", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man made over a billion dollars on September 16, 1992, known as Black Wednesday, because this man held a ten billion dollar short position on the pound; as a result, he became known as \u201cthe man who broke the Bank of England.\u201d Charter 77 and Solidarity were among the political groups funded by this man, who has been a common target of American right-wing pundits and anti-Semites. For ten points, name this Hungarian born founder of the philanthropic Open Society Foundations, a liberal activist and investor.", "answer": "George<b> Soros</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "William Gilpin was the first governor of this territory, where Lewis Ralston found gold at a creek now named for him. George Custer won the Battle of Washita River in this territory where, in 1864, volunteers under John Chivington massacred members of the Cheyenne and Arapaho tribes. President Grant made this territory a state in 1876. For ten points, name this territory to which the \u201cFifty-Niners\u201d migrated during the Pike\u2019s Peak Gold Rush.", "answer": "<b> Colorado</b> Territory", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "The memorial includes an inscription of the opening bars of this song, legendarily the last song played by the<em> Titanic</em> musicians as the ship sank.", "answer": "<b> Nearer, My God, to Thee</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This battle\u2019s losing commander declared that \u201cwe are in the chamber pot\u201d after falling into a trap near La Moncelle. A failed attempt to break out at Floing led to the death of Jean Margueritte during this battle. Officer casualties in this battle forced Auguste (+) Ducrot to take command before he, too, was replaced by Emmanuel Wimpffen. This battle began when Patrice MacMahon attempted to lift the Siege of Metz, only to be surrounded. The (*) </b> Second French Empire fell after, for ten points, what battle of the Franco-Prussian War that led to the capture of Napoleon III?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Sedan</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Octavio Paz invited this man to a 1990 conference where he cited the example of the PRI to claim that \u201cMexico is the perfect dictatorship.\u201d As a FREDEMO party candidate, this man won the first round of a 1990 presidential election but lost the run-off to a dark horse candidate from the right-wing Cambio 90 ticket, (+) Alberto Fujimori. The dictatorship of</b> <b>Manuel Odria is the setting of</b><em><b> Conversation in the Cathedral</b></em><b>, a (*)</b> novel by, for ten points, what Peruvian politician and author of<em> Aunt Julia and the Scriptwriter</em> who won the 2010 Nobel Prize in Literature?", "answer": "Mario<b> Vargas Llosa</b> (prompt on partial last names)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>Elizabeth Drinker unsuccessfully appealed to this woman in an attempt to free a group of Quaker soldiers who failed to give a loyalty oath. This woman\u2019s marriage to Daniel Parke</b> <b>Custis ended with his death, leaving her with over 300 (+)</b> <b>slaves and a massive estate</b> <b>at age 25. In 1777, this woman attended a production of the play</b><em><b> Cato</b></em><b> put on by soldiers at (*) </b> Valley Forge during a visit to meet her more famous second husband. For ten points, name this matriarch of Mount Vernon, the wife of George Washington.", "answer": "Martha<b> Washington</b> (accept Martha<b> Dandridge</b>; accept Martha<b> Custis</b> before \u201cCustis\u201d is mentioned) (4) <b>The remains of dome shaped huts have been found on this island at Mount Sandel.</b> <b>Hundreds of wedge tombs, including the Hag\u2019s Bed, were built facing the setting sun in the</b> <b>north of this island. This island\u2019s Neolithic monument (+)</b> <b>Newgrange features a burial</b> <b>chamber that lights up during the winter solstice; that monument is found just west of Drogheda [draw-duh] on the (*) </b> River Boyne. For ten points, name this European island that was settled by the Gaels before the 1169 Norman invasion from Britain to the east. ANSWER:<b> Ireland</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man, who was nominated for an Oscar as a producer on a 1960 film about the (+) Alamo, won his only Oscar in 1969 for playing Rooster Cogburn in (*)</b><em> True</em> <em>Grit</em>.<em> The Shootist</em>,<em> The Searchers</em>, and<em> Stagecoach</em> are among the over 100 films to feature, for ten points, what American western film star?", "answer": "John<b> Wayne</b> (accept Marion<b> Morrison</b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b>During this battle, one side\u2019s advances up Edson\u2019s Ridge forced the other side to call up reinforcements from the Kokoda Track. Supplies in this battle were taken down \u201cthe slot\u201dunder a system known as the Tokyo Express. This battle was codenamed Operation (+) Watchtower and featured the capture of Savo and Tulagi Islands. This battle was initiated to capture the airstrip at (*)</b> Henderson Field, which was to be used as a base for further attacks in the Pacific. For ten points, name this 1943 battle over a namesake island in the Solomons.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Guadalcanal</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This leader was supported by the British contingency plan Giralda, which would have prevented a coup attempt by the rival Umma party. Many of this leader\u2019s reforms were undone by the \u201ceverything goes\u201d policy of successor Ali Mwinyi. Following a dispute over</b> <b>his country\u2019s (+)</b> <b>Kagera region, this leader restored Milton Obote to power in Uganda</b> <b>Kagera region, this leader restored Milton Obote to power in Uganda</b> <b>over the defeated Idi Amin. This leader\u2019s policy of (*)</b> <b>over the defeated Idi Amin. This leader\u2019s policy of (*)</b> ujamaa was outlined in his Arusha Declaration, a manifesto of African socialism. Zanzibar and Tanganyika were unified during the tenure of, for ten points, what first president of Tanzania?", "answer": "Julius<b> Nyerere</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>J.M. Carter argued that the losing commander knew he was trapped at this battle, where he employed a quasi-horseshoe formation. Gaius Sosius commanded the left</b> <b>side of one force in this battle, whose center was led by Lucius (+)</b> <b>Arruntius. The</b> <em><b>Res Gestae</b></em><b> chronicles this battle. The winning side of this battle employed a large quantity of (*) </b> Liburnian ships at this battle to counter quinqueremes. An Egyptian queen aided one side at this battle, whose winner went on to earn the title Augustus. For ten points, name this 31 BC naval battle in which Octavian defeated Mark Antony.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Actium </b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}